So, what does it actually mean to be an
American? We talked about it in unit
two. We talked about it in unit 3, and
here we are in unit four, and we're just
going to keep right on talking about.
And the fact that it shows up so much in
our history makes me start to think that
maybe this is kind of an important
question to answer. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Okay, so if you've paid attention
over the last few units, then you'll no
doubt remember that in every period, all
kinds of Americans have been wrestling
with the notion of what it actually
means to be an American. I'm [music] not
like other countries. You see, for most
of the colonial period, the answer to
the question was to be, you know, like
more British. During the revolutionary
and founding era, the answer was that
Americans were people who love liberty.
And to be absolutely clear, those
answers to the American identity
question were the answers of the
majority. There were, of course,
minority groups who reckoned with a
different conception of American
identity, namely enslaved and free black
Americans, American Indians, and women.
Regardless, for the most part, during
those periods, much of the American
identity was a borrowed identity from
other places in the world. Oh, and by
the way, if you want note guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
then get that clicky finger out and
check the link in the description.
Anyway, during this period, we're going
to see a big shift in the way Americans
begin to answer this question. And in a
lot of ways, Americans are going to
start to develop a uniquely American
identity. I told you I'm not like other
countries. Anyway, one of the big causes
of this explosion of new ideas about
identity was what became known as the
era of good feelings that lasted roughly
from 1815 to 1825. It was a period of
intense nationalism that arose right
after the US victory against Great
Britain in the War of 1812. And here's
where I place heavy quotes on victory
because if you'll recall, it was kind of
a stalemate and both sides agreed to
return everything the way it was before
the war started. So, as I said in an
early video, it wasn't that the US
really won the war. It was more like
they just didn't lose it. But baby, that
was surely enough for Americans to puff
up their chest and be like America.
Anyway, the point is as Americans got
positively drunk on nationalism, it
began to feel something like an
emergency to develop a national identity
and culture that was uniquely American.
And so, starting around 1815, that
fervor was channeled into an amazingly
fertile period for new American cultural
expressions. And I reckon there's no
better place to start than by
considering how American identity was
revealed and reckoned with through art
during this period. Now, before I go and
start throwing riers and painters and
all the rest at you, I need to tell you
about the movement that inspired and
created the rules for America's
burgeoning artists. It was a European
artistic movement known as romanticism
and it was very much a reaction against
enlightenment thought and neocclassical
forms. If you'll recall, the
enlightenment emphasized the
thinkythinky parts which is to say
rational thought and sense experience is
the only path to truth. And then
neocclassical artists emphasized harmony
and symmetry like you can see here in
Gilbert Stewart's famous portrait of
George Washington. Like when you look at
this, maybe it provokes appreciation or
awe, but it sure ain't no mind-blowing
slap your mama kind of experience. And
that is where romanticism comes in with
its emphasis on emotional exuberance and
imaginative exploration and spontaneity.
Like compare Gilbert Stewart's
Washington to Emanuel Lutz's Washington
crossing the Delaware painted in 1851. I
mean, you look at this one and you're
like, hm, okay, okay. But then you look
at this one and you're like, oh,
[groaning]
and that's the whole point of
romanticism. These artists wanted you to
feel crap. Okay, so now that all that's
established, let me give you some
examples. As far as visual art goes,
it's hard to find a better example than
the Hudson River School of Artists. It
represented a significant shift from the
revolutionary era painters who majored
in painting people and glorifying
America's heroes. Instead, painters in
the Hudson River School made nature
their subject and painted majestic
American landscapes that called for more
of an emotional rather than rational
response from the viewer. And then in
terms of literature, a massive number of
unique American writers emerged during
this period as well. First, you had
James Fenomore Cooper whose novel last
of the Moheakans romanticized the
opportunity and danger of the mysterious
western frontier of America. His aim was
to contrast what he called the natural
men of the frontier with the men who had
been corrupted by civilization. And so
in his work, there's a big emphasis on
the values of the frontier as a key
ingredient in American identity. And
then you had Washington Irving who wrote
popular works like Rip Van Winkle and
The Legend of Sleepy Hollow that recast
America's landscape and people into a
world of fantasy. And because his books
were widely read in Europe as well, his
works acted as a kind of translation
tool to help Europeans understand
Americans and vice versa. Okay, so
here's where I have to slow down for a
second because you also need to realize
that regional identities were still very
powerful during this period even if
Americans were working very hard to
forge a national identity. You can't
forget about the regional variations
because not all Americans are thinking
about the identity question in the same
way. So for example, in terms of
literature, American writers during this
age wrote about the triumph of the
individual human being. Both Cooper and
Irving who were New Yorkers were
skeptical of the idea of human
perfectability that would later be
wholesale embraced by utopians and
philosophers. But still, the humans in
their stories were triumphant and
heroic. But if you want a regional
variation on this theme, then it's hard
to do better than our boy Edgar Allan
Poe, who himself was a Virginia. Now Po,
though he was still squarely in the
romantic camp, stands in stark contrast
to the theme of human perfectability and
wrote characters who were more like
anti-heroes and had deep and abiding
flaws. And though he was a master of
lyric poetry, this darker side meant
that he found more willing readers in
Europe than in America, where everybody
was drinking deep of the era of good
feelings. And then finally, before we
move on, let me briefly mention new
American styles of architecture that
emerged. Now, prior to this period, much
American architecture styling was
borrowed from the old world, and with a
few exceptions, buildings were built
according to the rules of
neocclassicism. But starting in the
1820s, American architects got busy
designing metric buttloadads of
buildings in the Greek revival style. It
was inspired by the Greek Revolution
against the Ottoman Empire during this
very same period, and it was an homage
to the two countries mutual love of
democracy. And again, that became a
significant ingredient in the emerging
American identity. Okay. Okay. And now
to round things out, let's talk about
the emergence of a uniquely American
philosophy that emerged during this time
and it was known as transcendentalism.
Now this way of thinking was also deeply
influenced by romanticism with its
emphasis on exuberance and emotion. It
was a clear rejection of the rationalism
of enlightenment thought which said that
truth can be known only through the
senses and through observation and
experimentation. Transcendentalists on
the other hand believed that truth was
beyond the senses or you know like
transcended them and therefore must be
accessed by other means chiefly by
communion with the mysteries of nature.
And just for poops and giggles, let me
introduce you to three of the luminaries
of the transcendentalist movement.
First, meet Ralph Waldo Emerson, who was
sort of the founding father of the
transcendentalist. Emerson furiously
wrote essays that emphasized the key
tenants of his new philosophy, and his
primary themes were nearly always
self-reliance and individual freedom.
And so, these two ideas again became a
key ingredient in the American identity.
Second, meet Henry David Theorough, who
was a friend of Emerson and ended up
writing one of the most important texts
of the transcendentalist movement,
namely Walden. Essentially, this book
chronicles the two years Theo spent
living in a small cabin in the woods. It
is positively filled with romantic
reflections on the beauty and abundance
of nature and the necessity to perfect
oneself by escaping the corrupting
influence of modern civilization through
solitude and silence.
>> So romantic. And then third, meet
Margaret Fuller, who helped spread the
New American philosophy to elite circles
of women who lived in Boston. And
influenced by the transcendentalist
emphasis on the exaltation of all
individuals, she wrote woman in the 19th
century in 1845 in which she harshly
criticized the rigid gender roles that
kept American women from true equality.
And later in this period, this work is
going to be a touchstone of the growing
movement for women's rights. But we'll
have to save that juicy tale for another
video. Okay, you can click here to watch
my other unit 4 videos, or you can click
here to grab my video note guides, which
is going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly crammed
into your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch you on the
flipflop. I am the wreck.